Wilton Historical Society Manuscript Collection
Wilton History Room, Wilton Historical Society
Wilton Historical Society Manuscript Collection
1640-present
Wilton Historical Society (Wilton, Conn.)
MAN
50 linear feet / 6 drawers, 1 map drawer, 10 boxes, 179 daybooks and ledgers, 74 diaries and journals.
Wilton History Room, Wilton Historical Society
The Wilton Historical Society Manuscript Collection contains diaries and journals, daybooks and ledgers, school records, correspondence, literary works, and the collected papers of early Wilton families and prominent individual residents. The bulk of the collection is from the nineteenth and twentieth centuries, but important items from the eighteenth and seventeenth centuries are also included.
Restrictions
Collection open for research.
Acquisition Information
The Wilton Historical Society Manuscript Collection was compiled by the Wilton Historical Society.
History
1. Wilton Historical Society Manuscript Collection
The Wilton Historical Society, founded in 1938, collected numerous manuscripts pertaining to Wilton families and local history. Additions have been made by Carol Russell, Wilton Historical Society Archivist and Wilton Town Historian. The majority of the collection was created in Wilton and by Wilton residents, but correspondence received by Wilton residents from non-resident friends and family is also included. In addition, several daybooks and ledgers were created outside Wilton, but include Wilton family names. Likewise, some diaries and journals were produced outside Wilton, but by Wilton residents.
2. Wilton History Room
The Wilton History Room is a unique collaboration between the Wilton Historical Society (WHS) and the Wilton Library Association (WLA). Compiled beginning in 1938, the archival collections of the Wilton Historical Society had been stored in the 18th century Fitch House. In 1980, the officers and trustees of the WHS, in conversation with the director and board members of the WLA, determined that a climate controlled space, improved organization, and better public accessibility were necessary; and so in January 1984 they established a home for the collection in the Wilton Library. Organization of the collections was supported by the Cudlipp Memorial Fund and undertaken by Carol Russell. The Wilton Historical Society has retained its ownership, while the Wilton Library maintains the collections, and provides access and assistance to patrons.
The Wilton History Room is one of the most complete, organized, and well-staffed historical research facilities, for a town of our size, in Fairfield County. It is financed by the WLA, The Russell Fund, and The History Room Fund.
The Wilton History Room is one of the most complete, organized, and well-staffed historical research facilities, for a town of our size, in Fairfield County. It is supported by the WHS, the WLA, The Russell Fund, The History Room Fund, local non-profit organizations, individual donors, and community volunteers.
Scope and Content of Collection
Major series within the Wilton Historical Society Manuscripts Collection include the Cannon Store Daybooks and Ledgers, the Betts-Raymond Store Papers, the David Hermon Van Hoosear Papers, and the G. Evans Hubbard Papers. Customer information, lists of goods purchased, and detailed accounts are included in the Cannon Store Daybooks and Ledgers and the Betts-Raymond Store Papers. The latter series also includes some correspondence. The David Hermon Van Hoosear Papers primarily consist of notes on and hand-written copies of the original materials David Hermon Van Hoosear (1844-1921), the distinguished local historian and author, consulted as he researched Wilton history, early Wilton families, and the history and families of neighboring towns. Original materials collected by David Hermon Van Hoosear are included as well. The G. Evans Hubbard Papers contain the personal papers, correspondence, and property records of G. Evans Hubbard (1891-1950), another eminent local historian and author. In addition, this series includes court records from G. Evans Hubbard's service as a trial justice, as well as records of his social works and community engagement.
Family names in the collection include: Abbott, Adams, Allee, Allen, Ambler, Arnold, Ayres, Beardsley, Bedient, Belden, Benedict, Bennett, Berry, Bethel, Betts, Birchard, Blackmar, Bouton, Bowles, Brewster, Brown, Browne, Campbell, Cannon, Chandler, Chichester, Clerc, Cole, Comstock, Condit, Crookshank, Darling, Davenport, Davis, DeForest, Dewing, DeWitt, Douglas, Emler, Ferris, Fillow, Finch, Fisher, Fitch, Gaylord, Gilbert, Godfrey, Gorham, Gregory, Grumman, Hallock, Hallock, Handricks, Hanford, Harper, Hawley, Hedburg, Hill, Homan, Hoyt, Hubbard, Hubbell, Hurlbutt, Hyatt, Ingram, Jackson, James, Jelif, Jennings, Jones, Keeler, Knapp,. Lambert, Little, Lockwood, Lynch, Lyon, Marvin, Mason, McKeever, Mead, Budd, Merwin, Middlebrook, Miller, Morehouse, Morgan, Nash, Nichols, Ogden, Olmstead, Pardee, Post, Proctor, Quick, Raymond, Reed, Resseguie, Reynolds, Richards, Rock, Rockwell, Rusco (Ruscoe) Russell, Sackmann, Sanford, Schenck, Scott, Seymour, Shepherd, Sherwood, Shoemaker, Sloan, Smith, St. John, Steichen, Sterling, Sturges, Sutton, Taylor, Telford, Terrel, Trowbridge, Turner, Tuttle, Moran, Van Zandt, Wakeman, Wakeman, Weitzel, Wells, Westcott, Whitlock, Whittlesey, Willard, Williams, Wilson, Winton, Winton, Wittwell, and Youman.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged by item format, and then by family name, individual, and topic. Diaries and journals, oversize manuscripts, and daybooks and ledgers are shelved or boxed. Loose papers are filed.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Accounts.; Agriculture.; Cemeteries.; Church records and registers.; Correspondence.; Courtship.; Diaries.; Hubbard, G. Evans, 1891-1950.; Legal documents.; Literature.; Livestock.; Municipal courts.; Municipal government.; Schools.; Soldiers.; Van Hoosear, D. H. (David Hermon), 1844.-; Wars.
Related Collections
Researchers should also consult the Wilton History Room's book collection and its other major collections. The Wilton Historical Information Collection (WHI) in particular contains typed and printed materials from many of the same sources and covering many of the same topics as the handwritten materials in the Manuscripts Collection.
Separated Material
Select additional manuscripts are in the Wilton Historical Society Museum.
- 1. Daybooks and ledgers
  - Daybooks and ledgers in boxes
    - Cannon Store account book, 1847-1849; This item is stored in a box. (Box 1, Item 12)
    - Cannon Store blotter, 1851-1857; This item is stored in a box. (Box 3, Item 39)
    - Cannon Store blotter, 1853; This item is stored in a box. (Box 4, Item 45)
    - Cannon Store check payroll, 1851-1852; This is a payroll daybook. It is stored in a box. (Box 3, Item 36)
    - Cannon Store daybooks, 1846-1849; These five volumes cover the years 1846-1849. These items are stored in a box. (Box 1, Item 7, 8, 10, 13, 14)
    - Cannon Store daybooks, 1849-1851; These four volumes cover the years 1849-1851. These items are stored in a box. (Box 2, Item 18, 19, 22, 25)
    - Cannon Store daybooks, 1850-1852; These items are stored in a box. (Box 3, Item 29, 30, 32, 33, 40, 41)
    - Cannon Store daybooks, 1852-1856; These items are stored in a box. (Box 4, Item 43, 48)
    - Cannon Store invoices, 1849-1853; These items are stored in a box. (Box 2, Item 20, 27)
    - Cannon Store invoices - Otis and Perry, 1852; This is a volume of invoices pertaining to clothing sent out on consignment. This item is stored in a box. (Box 4, Item 42)
    - Cannon Store invoices - Otis, John and Company, 1849-1850; This is a volume of invoices pertaining to clothing sent out on consignment. These items are stored in a box. (Box 2, Item 23, 24)
    - Cannon Store invoices - Trowbridge Dwight and Company, 1853-1857; This item is stored in a box. (Box 4, Item 46)
    - Cannon Store ladies blotter, 1849; This item is stored in a box. (Box 2, Item 16)
    - Cannon Store ledger, 1851-1852; This item is stored in a box. (Box 3, Item 37)
    - Cannon Store railroad pay records, 1851; These records pertain to the Danbury and Norwalk Railroad. They are stored in a box. (Box 3, Item 35)
    - Cannon Store sewing records, undated; This book records clothing measurements. It is stored in a box. (Box 1, Item 1)
    - Cannon Store sewing records, 1849; This volume contains records of clothes sewn. It is stored in a box. (Box 2, Item 17)
  - Daybooks and ledgers on shelves
    - Abbott, George, 1861-1893; These are the Hurlbutt Street blacksmith's daybooks. There are five volumes, covering the years 1861-1863, 1866-1870, 1870-1873, 1873-1886, and 1886-1893. (Box shelves, Item 118, 119, 120, 121, 122)
    - Ambler and Youman, undated; This is an alphabetical account book. (Box shelves, Item 5)
    - Ambler family, 1942-1967; These books record disbursements from the Ambler estate. There are three volumes, covering 1942-1954, 1954-1962, and 1962-1967. (Box shelves, Item 141, 142, 143)
    - Ambler family, 1942-1962; These books record cash payments and rental income to the Ambler estate. There are two volumes, covering 1942-1954 and 1954-1962. (Box shelves, Item 144, 145)
    - Ambler family, 1942-1950; This is a general accounts book. (Box shelves, Item 146)
    - Anonymous, 1818-1831; This is a farmer's record book of cider sales. (Box shelves, Item 4)
    - Anonymous, 1856-1862; This is a liquor store ledger written in New York. (Box shelves, Item 10)
    - Anonymous, 1841; This is a book of sales accounts. (Box shelves, Item 46)
    - Anonymous, 1841-1842; This is a book of general accounts kept in New York state. (Box shelves, Item 52)
    - Anonymous, 1847-1852; This is an account book, including list of "sundries by and to." (Box shelves, Item 59)
    - Anonymous, 1813-1814; This is a book of cash accounts. (Box shelves, Item 61)
    - Anonymous, 1857-1860; This is a book of personal accounts. (Box shelves, Item 63)
    - Anonymous, 1863-1804; This is a store account book and scrapbook. (Box shelves, Item 73)
    - Anonymous, 1840; This is an unidentified hatter's book of notes and accounts. (Box shelves, Item 91)
    - Anonymous, 1839-1842; This is an unidentified cobbler's account book. (Box shelves, Item 109)
    - Anonymous, 1862; These are personal accounts; possibly from the Ogden family. (Box shelves, Item 114)
    - Anonymous, 1791-1817; This is a records book of house building costs, material, labor, and interest. (Box shelves, Item 128)
    - Anonymous, 1843-1884; This is a book recording military subjects, including enlistment dates, exemptions, and reasons for exemptions granted. (Box shelves, Item 134)
    - Bald Hill School, 1862-1868; This is a book of attendance records. (Box shelves, Item 124)
    - Benedict, Frederick R., 1855-1878; This is a store and account book, recording purchase and production of leather goods such as shoes, book bindings, etc. (Box shelves, Item 111)
    - Betts, Asahel Raymond, 1812-1820; This is an account book index. (Box shelves, Item 60)
    - Betts, Captain Daniel, 1809-1817; This is a daybook. (Box shelves, Item 55)
    - Betts, Captain Daniel and Captain Asahel Raymond, 1800-1803; This is a general store ledger. See also estate inventory of Asahel R. Betts, 1827. (Box shelves, Item 3)
    - Betts, Lewis, 1817-1841; This is a book of general accounts. (Box shelves, Item 39)
    - Betts, Sherman and Asahel Raymond, 1812-1819; This is a book of store accounts. (Box shelves, Item 56)
    - Brewster, George and William Nichols, 1846-1870; This is a general accounts book. (Box shelves, Item 21)
    - Cannon Store account book, 1873-1875; These two volumes cover the years 1873-1875 and 1880-1889. Account book 61 records expenses. (Box shelves, Item 54, 61)
    - Cannon Store daybook - D. C. H. Brown's meat market, 1876-1877; These two daybooks record purchases at D. C. H. Brown's meat market, South Norwalk. (Box shelves, Item 57, 58)
    - Cannon Store daybooks, 1817-1844; Daybook 2 includes a diary excerpt. Daybook 11 includes accounts. These seventeen volumes cover the years 1817-1818, 1836-1858, and 1878-1884. (Box shelves, Item 2, 4, 5, 6, 9, 11, 15, 31, 34, 38, 44, 47, 49, 50, 51, 60, 62)
    - Cannon Store ladies blotter, 1858-1858; This item is MISSING. (Box shelves, Item 52)
    - Cannon Store ledger, 1872-1876; This ledger contains orders from H. D. West's meat market, South Norwalk. (Box shelves, Item 53)
    - Cannon Store ledgers, 1817-1818; These six volumes cover the years 1817-1818, 1849-1857, 1872-1877, and 1885-1890. (Box shelves, Item 3, 21, 28, 56, 59, 64)
    - Cannon Store sewing records, 1849-1853; This volume contains records of clothes sewn. (Box shelves, Item 26)
    - Cannon Store shipments, 1885-1889; This book records shipments made to a wire mill. (Box shelves, Item 63)
    - Cannon, Charles, 1893; This is a ledger for the Cannon farm, including Charles Cannon's estate records. (Box shelves, Item 137)
    - Cole, Nichols and Company, 1850-1851; This is an account book of the carriage and wagon making company. (Box shelves, Item 23)
    - Cole, Nichols and Company, 1848-1851; This is a repair work account book of the carriage and wagon making company. (Box shelves, Item 24)
    - Cole, Nichols and Company, 1833-1876; These are general accounts books of the carriage and wagon making company. There are two volumes, covering 1833-1844 and 1846-1876. (Box shelves, Item 38, 45)
    - Cole, Nichols and Company, 1838-1847; These are four daybooks of the carriage and wagon making company, III. 1838-1839, IV. 1842-1844, V. 1846, and VI. 1846-1847. (Box shelves, Item 64, 65, 66, 67)
    - Cole, Sherman, 1833-1834; These are two daybooks, I. 1833-1834 and II. 1835-1838. (Box shelves, Item 68, 69)
    - Comstock, James, 1860-1864; This is a ledger for a general store. (Box shelves, Item 8)
    - Condit and Bowles, 1840; This is a ledger kept in New York state. (Box shelves, Item 53)
    - Crookshank, D. George and Sam L. Lambert, 1841-1848; This is an account book. (Box shelves, Item 90)
    - Dog warden, 1898-1908; These are dog and kennel account records. (Box shelves, Item 113)
    - E. Hoyt and Company, 1873-1877; This is a daily ledger, probably kept by a stationer selling folios and legal papers. (Box shelves, Item 57)
    - Gilbert, Eli, 1841-1842; These are the hardware and commission merchant's Connecticut sales and accounts books. There are two volumes, covering the years 1841 and 1842. (Box shelves, Item 9, 47)
    - Gilbert, Eli, 1840-1858; These are the hardware and commission merchant's cash and business accounts books and ledgers written in New York. There are four volumes, covering 1840-1841, 1841-1843, 1842-1843, and 1857-1858. (Box shelves, Item 11, 12, 13, 50)
    - Gregory, Thaddeus, 1733-1738; This is an accounts book, including notations relating to a calendar change and genealogy on page 3. (Box shelves, Item 1)
    - Hoyt, Edgar, 1872-1875; This is a bank book. (Box shelves, Item 58)
    - Hoyt, Louisa Lyon, 1900-1915; This is Louisa Lyon Hoyt's cash book. (Box shelves, Item 88)
    - Hoyt, Solomon, 1834-1848; This is a Stamford blacksmith's repair and general accounts books. There are three volumes, covering the years 1834-1835, 1836-1837, and 1846-1848. (Box shelves, Item 30, 31, 32)
    - Hurlbutt, Daniel, 1759-1790; This is a book of weaving records, including genealogical information in the back. It is MISSING. (Box shelves, Item 133)
    - Hurlbutt, David, 1827-1861; This is a ledger. (Box shelves, Item 125)
    - Hurlbutt, Henry Clay, 1856-1868; These are New York state business accounts; some Wilton names are included. There are six ledgers. (Box shelves, Item 110)
    - Knapp, C. W., 1807-1828; This is an account book. (Box shelves, Item 136)
    - Lime Rock Iron Company, 1867-1869; This is the company's ore book. (Box shelves, Item 112)
    - M., C. W., 1836-1852; This is a book of general accounts kept in New York state. (Box shelves, Item 51)
    - Mead, Lyman, 1824-1850; This is a book kept by the shoemaker Lyman Mead. (Box shelves, Item 44)
    - Middlebrook family, 1831-1854; This is a book of estates and payroll accounts. (Box shelves, Item 19)
    - Middlebrook, Michael, 1849-1849; This is a general accounts book with newspaper clippings relating to hardware. It was written in Ballston, New York. (Box shelves, Item 18)
    - Middlebrook, Samuel, 1807-1808; This is a book of store records. (Box shelves, Item 54)
    - Morgan, Aaron and Chauncey Keeler, 1819-1831; These are the blacksmiths' account books. There are two volumes, covering the years 1819-1823 and 1825-1831. (Box shelves, Item 33, 34)
    - New York ledger, 1859-1862; This is a general store ledger, containing orders for cider, brandy, tea, cigars, potatoes, etc., alongside many Wilton names. (Box shelves, Item 15)
    - New York ledger, 1856-1859; This is a general store ledger, containing orders for cider, brandy, tea, cigars, potatoes, etc., alongside many Wilton names. (Box shelves, Item 14)
    - New York, New Haven, and Hartford Railroad Company, 1874-1916; These are freight account books, including foreign freight received at Cannon Station. There are three volumes, covering 1874-1877, 1892-1911, and 1892-1916. (Box shelves, Item 7, 116, 117)
    - Nichols, David C., 1809-1838; Repair accounts (Box shelves, Item 29)
    - Nichols, David C., 1840-1851; This is a book of general accounts. (Box shelves, Item 42)
    - Nichols, George S., 1847-1866; These are general and cash accounts books. There are five volumes covering the years 1847-1848, 1848-1849, 1851-1853, 1851-1860, and 1854-1866. (Box shelves, Item 22, 25, 26, 27, 28)
    - Nichols, George S. and William, 1831-1874; These are general accounts books. There are two volumes, covering 1864-1874 and 1831-1841. (Box shelves, Item 41, 43)
    - Ogden, Joseph, 1774-1860; This is a general accounts book; it also contains genealogical information on the Ogden, Sturgis, Hurlbutt, and Andrews families. (Box shelves, Item 16)
    - Olmstead, Daniel G., 1855-1895; This is an account book of payments made and received for labor, equipment, and laborers supplied. (Box shelves, Item 126)
    - Olmstead, Harry, 1919-1935; This is a book of farm accounts. (Box shelves, Item 131)
    - Olmstead, Hawley, 1818-1821; This is a school ledger. (Box shelves, Item 87)
    - Olmstead, Walter D., 1826-1871; These are farm accounts books. There are two volumes, covering the years 1826-1850, and 1844-1871. (Box shelves, Item 74, 127)
    - Quick, T. S., 1846-1850; These are blacksmith T. S. Quick's book of general accounts. There are two volumes, covering 1846-1848 and 1848-1850. (Box shelves, Item 37, 40)
    - Raymond, Samuel S., 1851-1853; "Count Book" or accounts book, recording payments in kind and cash for various services, including shoeing horses. (Box shelves, Item 17)
    - Raymond, William M., 1832-1855; These are grocery accounts books. There are two volumes, covering the years 1835-1847 and 1832-1855. (Box shelves, Item 71, 72)
    - School Committee, District #10, 1852-1872; This is a records book. A copy is located in MC-7. (Box shelves, Item 70)
    - Scott, Colonel Samuel, 1822-1862; These are daybooks. There are two volumes, covering 1822-1862 and 1830. (Box shelves, Item 6, 35)
    - Scott, Harry, 1856-1875; This is a book of general accounts. (Box shelves, Item 49)
    - Scott, Samuel, 1828-1829; This is a daybook with many entries for rum, whiskey, brandy, etc. (Box shelves, Item 36)
    - Smith, Jesse, 1831-1835; This is a daybook. (Box shelves, Item 2)
    - Sterling, Nathaniel and C. W. Knapp, 1828-1858; This is a daybook. (Box shelves, Item 135)
    - Sterling, William, 1741-1828; This is the storekeeper’s journal. It covers the years 1741, 1753-1773, and 1829. It was acquired from the Ambler estate. (Box shelves, Item 140)
    - Sturges, John B., 1875; This is a book of poultry raising accounts. (Box shelves, Item 75)
    - Sturges, Samuel Burr, 1847-1872; This is a personal accounts book. (Box shelves, Item 132)
    - Town of Wilton, 1871-1903; This is a ledger of receipts and expenses, including ”Outstanding Orders." (Box shelves, Item 20)
    - Town of Wilton School Committee, 1911-1937; These are school accounts books. There are three volumes, covering the years 1911-1929, 1929-1933, and 1929-1937. (Box shelves, Item 130, 138, 139)
    - Wakeman, L. H., 1890; This is the account book of L. H. Wakeman's estate. (Box shelves, Item 108.1)
    - Wakeman, Sarah E., 1887-1895; This is a book of Sarah E. Wakeman's personal accounts. (Box shelves, Item 108.2)
    - Wakeman, William, 1867-1881; This is a record of William Wakeman's personal savings account. (Box shelves, Item 108.3)
    - Weitzel, Charles W., 1931; This is the plumber Charles W. Weitzel's daybook. (Box shelves, Item 115)
    - Wilton / Norwalk, 1856-1862; This is an account book for a store that served Wilton and South Norwalk. (Box shelves, Item 48)
    - Winton, Benjamin, 1840-1846; This is an account book for sales of cider, apples, and brandy. (Box shelves, Item 62)
    - Zion Hill Methodist Church Sunday School, 1934-1936; This is a book of attendance records. (Box shelves, Item 129)
- 2. Diaries and journals
  - Adams, Charles Nathan, 1894-1898; These are five diaries for the years 1894, 1895, 1896, 1897 (April through December), and 1898. (Box shelves, Item 41, 42, 43, 44, 45)
  - Ambler family, 1916; This is an accounting of taxes, repairs, and insurance on properties owned. (Box shelves, Item 72)
  - Ambler, Hannah Raymond, 1861-1924; These are twenty-two diaries of daily happenings, also including recipes, accounts, and hand-copied text from newspaper clippings. Diaries held are for the years 1861, 1899-1903, 1905-1907, 1909-1916, 1918-21, along with a single volume covering 1922-1924. (Box shelves, Item 51, 52, 53, 54, 55, 56, 57, 58, 59, 60, 61, 62, 63, 64, 65, 66, 67, 68, 69, 70, 71, 74)
  - Ambler, Hannah Raymond, undated; This is a inventory of books and bookcases in the Raymond-Ambler house. (Box shelves, Item 73)
  - Anonymous, 1885; This item number includes seven diaries. The handwriting is difficult to read. (Box shelves, Item 4)
  - Anonymous, 1872; This is a diary of daily happenings. It includes recipe for sponge cake and cures for various ailments. (Box shelves, Item 14)
  - Anonymous, 1874; This is a diary of daily happenings with weather notations. It includes two photographs. The author is the same as that of Diary 15. (Box shelves, Item 17)
  - Anonymous, 1862; This diary contains notes on daily activities and expenses. (Box shelves, Item 18)
  - Anonymous, 1878; This is a diary of daily happenings with weather notations. The author is the same as that of Diary 17. (Box shelves, Item 15)
  - Anonymous, 1899-1912; This is a daily diary including weather notations. (Box shelves, Item 7)
  - Bedient, Martha and Carrie, 1874; This is a book of recipes. (Box shelves, Item 31)
  - Bethel, Claudine M., 1901; This is a diary titled "My Southern Trip." (Box shelves, Item 37)
  - Ferris, Lockwood K., 1813-1895, 1845-1852; Lockwood K. Ferris was the son of Seth and Mary Keeler Ferris. (Box shelves, Item 2)
  - Finch, Jane A., 1893; This is a diary of daily happenings. (Box shelves, Item 36)
  - Finch, Jane A., 1883-1888; This is a name and address book also containing a record of accounts. (Box shelves, Item 16)
  - Finch, Mrs. Henry, 1896-1922; These are eight diaries of daily happenings for the years 1896, 1900, 1903, 1906-8, 1913, and 1922. (Box shelves, Item 22, 23, 24, 25, 26, 27, 28, 29)
  - Fitch-Sturges recipe book, 1889; This item is fragile. (Box shelves, Item 9)